Okay, בוקר
טוב. Boker Tov. We today's דף Daf at least for us is
נ"ט. Nun Tet. We'll see if we can get a little bit
closer to being caught up. We start with some משנה Mishnah on
נ"ט. Nun Tet. We had just read yesterday actually a little quickly,
but the end of the גמרא, Gemara, perfect segue into this משנה,
Mishnah, which is the whole discussion about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
who marries a woman when she is a קטנה Ketannah and then
she becomes a בוגרת. Bogeret. And does the fact that she became
a בוגרת Bogeret before he did נישואין, nissu'in, is the הלכה halakhah
about the קידושין kiddushin has to be when she's a קטנה Ketannah
or is the הלכה halakhah that the נישואין nissu'in has to be
when she's a קטנה? Ketannah? And the גמרא Gemara want to make
it based on the פסוקים, pesukim, but in the end said that
actually that would be a problem that she would have to be
a קטנה Ketannah even at the time of נישואין, nissu'in, although that's
not necessarily true about other situations, particularly cases where it's not the
woman who changed but he changed; he did the קידושין kiddushin when
he was a normal כהן kohen and then he became a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, then she might go by the previous state, the
state at the time of the קידושין. kiddushin. Anyway, what is relevant
is that we introduced the idea of the special הלכות halakhot restrictions
that apply to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when it comes to
marriage, more than a normal כהן. kohen. One of them, which is
not necessarily clear in the פסוקים, pesukim, it says אישה בבתוליה יקח,
ishah bive-tuleha yikkach, so it is clear that מצווה mitzvah to marry
a woman who is a בתולה, besulah, a virgin. What is not
clear is this issue that the גמרא Gemara took for granted to
marry her when she is a קטנה Ketannah or at least a
נערה na'arah but not when she is a בוגרת, Bogeret, not when
she has reached adulthood, you know, physical maturity which is assumed to
be twelve and a half. And then again the issue about does
that apply at קידושין kiddushin or at נישואין. nissu'in. So that with
that background, we look at this next משנה Mishnah which directly addresses
itself to those issues. Let's take a look. Okay, so now we
are you know, you probably aren't even aware about how far we've
drifted from the original topic, maybe because there isn't an original topic,
I don't know, but anyway this whole
מסכתא masekhta has to do about a brother-in-law.
Exactly, יבמות, Yevamot, but you know, but we are a lot of
יבמות Yevamot is about issues relating to status and permitted and forbidden
marriages and so on. So now we are well within the permitted
and forbidden marriages, particularly as it relates to כהונה. kehunah. So let's
take a look at the next משנה, Mishnah, at this משנה. Mishnah.
כהן גדול לא ישא אלמנה, Kohen Gadol lo yissa almanah,
okay, he cannot marry an אלמנה, almanah, that's in the תורה. Torah.
Notice, by the way, the word of ישא, yissa, נישואין, nissu'in, which
gets back to yesterday's discussions. בין אלמנה מן האירוסין בין אלמנה מן
הנישואין, Bein almanah min ha-erusin bein almanah min ha-nissu'in,
whether she's an אלמנה almanah from אירוסין erusin and therefore assumed to
be still a virgin, or whether she's an אלמנה מן הנישואין, almanah
min ha-nissu'in, it doesn't matter, the תורה Torah says he can't marry
an אלמנה. almanah.
Excuse me, ולא ישא בוגרת. ve-lo yissa bogeret. He cannot marry a
woman who is a בוגרת. Bogeret. There are three stages: נערה, na'arah,
קטנה Ketannah is under twelve and a day; from twelve and a
day to twelve and a half she's a נערה; na'arah; from twelve
and a half she is a בוגרת, Bogeret, which means a fully
mature, at least physically mature, and he cannot marry her once she's
a בוגרת, Bogeret, which is nowhere in the פסוקים. pesukim. רבי אלעזר
ורבי שמעון מכשירין בבוגרת. Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Shimon makhshirin be-vogeret. Rabbi Elazar
and Rabbi Shimon say, no, בוגרת Bogeret is not a problem. But
reading what we have in the what? Yeah, yeah, yeah. And but
reading what we have in the brackets, ולא, ve-lo, although question about
the actual גירסא girsa here, ולא ישא מוכת עץ. ve-lo yissa mukat
etz. And this is either דברי הכל divrei ha-kol or this is
Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon saying he cannot though marry a woman
who is literally smitten by wood, which means that which means that
she does not have her hymen not due to any act of
sex, but due to some other type of a physical activity, like
some actually thing, you know, some thing actually went up the vagina
and actually ruptured it or what happens more commonly today is just
due to physical activity in general it can rupture. Okay, and that's
a מוכת עץ. mukat etz. So basically, we don't care that she
is has matured, but what we do care is that the physical
hymen is intact. And that gets to the question of אישה בבתוליה.
ishah bive-tuleha. What does it mean to be a virgin? Is that
about the hymen or is that about sex? And that actually is
the issue that the גמרא Gemara turns itself to right away, because
one could imagine an act of sex which does not rupture the
hymen. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught.
Let's just go to the גמרא. Gemara. אלמנה לא יקח, Almanah lo
yikkach, he should not take an אלמנה. almanah.
בין אלמנה מן האירוסין בין אלמנה מן הנישואין, Bein almanah min ha-erusin
bein almanah min ha-nissu'in, it doesn't it doesn't distinguish, doesn't matter if
she's a widow from אירוסין erusin or נישואין. nissu'in. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously.
מהו דתימא, Mahu deteima, I might have thought, ליגמר אלמנה אלמנה מתמר.
ligmar almanah almanah mi-Tamar. Let's learn אלמנה almanah from תמר. Tamar. מה
להלן מן הנישואין אף כאן מן הנישואין. Mah lehalan min ha-nissu'in af
kan min ha-nissu'in. The same way from תמר Tamar it is from
נישואין, nissu'in, that was just the case. שבי אלמנה בית אביך, Shevi
almanah beit avikh, and she had had been נישואין nissu'in to, you
know, to the brothers, so obviously she was having sex and so
on. So maybe all אלמנות almanot should be read following that model?
קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, no, there's any אלמנה. almanah. ואימא
הכי נמי, Ve-eima hakhi nami, why not learn from תמר? Tamar? No.
דומיא דגרושה, Dumya de-gerushah, because it says he can't marry an אלמנה
וגרושה. almanah u-gerushah. את אלה לא יקח. et eleh lo yikach. So
אלמנה almanah like גרושה. grushah. מה גרושה בין מן האירוסין בין מן
הנישואין. ma grushah bein min ha-erusin bein min ha-nisuin.
The same way גרושה, grushah, there's no model of גרושה grushah to
limit it to נישואין. nisuin. גרושה grushah is סתם, stam, would apply
whether אירוסין erusin or נישואין. nisuin. אבל אלמנה, aval almanah, so even
אלמנה, almanah, even though there is the model of Tamar, בין מן
האירוסין בין מן הנישואין bein min ha-erusin bein min ha-nisuin doesn't make
a difference. Okay. Straight אלמנה almanah or גרושה, grushah, it's not about
not being a virgin, that's covered in the next פסוק: pasuk: אשה
בבתוליה. ishah bivtuleiha. And
therefore it does not matter whether אלמנה almanah or גרושה grushah from
אירוסין erusin or from נישואין. nisuin.
This somehow involves Judah and Tamar. ולא ישא בוגרת. v'lo yisah bogeret.
Now we get to this issue about the woman who is physically
mature. The גמרא Gemara says תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: והוא אשה בבתוליה
יקח, v'hu ishah bivtuleiha yikach, he shall take a woman in her
virginity, virginal status.
So, right again, it's a funny phrase. It could have said והוא
אשה בתולה יקח. v'hu ishah betulah yikach. So, בבתוליה, bivtuleiha, what does
that come to say? So, פרט לבוגרת שכלו לה בתוליה, prat l'bogeret
shekalu lah betuleiha, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So, Rabbi Meir
says this excludes a בוגרת bogeret who literally the בתולים betulim have
been dissipated, finished, no longer present. But תוספות Tosafot says clearly as
the גמרא Gemara is going to make clear, it doesn't mean don't
exist anymore, but somehow have thinned out, are not in the same,
are not as thick or as present as they were when she
was still a בוגרת, bogeret, when she was still younger. Again, I
should have done some checking about this. I don't know the anatomical
aspects about this.
But anyway,
well whatever, Charlie will check. Okay. But the גמרא's Gemara assumption here
is that once a woman reaches maturity, look, I mean,
even for various areas of הלכה, halachah, particularly about the issue about
the wedding night and דם בתולים dam betulim and whether a woman
is considered a נדה niddah after the hymen ruptures and so on,
there's an important question about whether the hymen is still considered to
be intact. And we've had various gynecologists or whatever come to the
ישיבה yeshiva and talk about those issues and they basically say that's
a question that doctors really hate and medical professionals, whatever, feel is
a bogus question because it's not like it's either there or it's
not there. In general the hymen is perforated and there's a question
about, even in a younger girl? Oh yeah, every hymen, and there's
a question about degree of perforation. It's not a question of it's
still there or not there. So therefore, you have to frame the
question a little bit differently. Anyway, but
the גמרא's Gemara assumption that again, that when she reaches בגרות, bagrut,
it's somehow in a different state. It's not like that doesn't happen
to the hymen. It thins out, it becomes more, it gets perforated,
but it's not like an all or nothing type of an issue.
Charlie, what did you find in the last two minutes here? Anything?
I haven't gotten to that yet. Okay, so it is clearly not,
a damaged hymen is clearly not necessarily a sign of
having had sexual intercourse.
Okay, that's מן הסתם. min hastam. But about whether the hymen
changes during the period of puberty is just a question. Anyway, that's
what the גמרא Gemara assumes. By the time puberty is over, the
hymen won't be exactly in the same state it was beforehand. So
let's get back to that. So, פרט לבוגרת שכלו בתוליה, prat l'bogeret
shekalu betuleiha, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So Rabbi Meir said
בבתוליה bivtuleiha implies full status of the hymen in its full state
and therefore once she is past puberty she's no longer considered in
that physical state. I know. No, well, I know, we'll see that
in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון מכשירין בבוגרת. Rabbi Elazar
v'Rabbi Shimon machshirin bivogeret. So Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon say no
problem. ובמאי קמיפלגי? uv'mai kamiflagi? Now where are they getting this from
the פסוקים? pesukim? רבי מאיר סבר בתולה Rabbi Meir savar betulah אפילו
מקצת בתולים משמע. afilu miktzat betulim mashma. Had the תורה Torah said
והוא אשה בתולה יקח, v'hu ishah betulah yikach,
בתולה betulah means even if there's some element of the hymen present.
It's a more inclusive phrase. Okay. בבתוליה, bivtuleiha, her בתולים, betulim, somehow
is a, somehow is like an intensifier, and maybe means in its
prime, or whatever, in its original state. So, עד דאיכא כל בתולים.
ad d'ika kol betulim. It means that the whole hymen has to
be there, or it has to be in its most unchanged state,
so prior to puberty.
בבתוליה, bivtuleiha, now what's the extra ב? bet? Why didn't it say
והוא אשה בתוליה? v'hu ishah betuleiha? Although that wouldn't make sense. Okay.
Anyway, כדרכה ולא שלא כדרכה. kedarkah v'lo shelo kedarkah. Somehow the extra
ב bet is coming to somehow say limit. Although the בבתוליה bivtuleiha
was coming to say that she's only considered a virgin when
the hymen is completely unchanged, but the בבתוליה bivtuleiha comes to tell
you that it's like a broadening, it's a limiting of the איסור,
issur, it's a broadening of the concept of virginity, which means that
it's only considered a problem if she's had vaginal sex. If she's
had anal sex, it's not a problem. So this is quite, quite
like shocking, but in a way quite logical, because what Rabbi Meir
is doing... is, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is looking completely at the
physical hymen and not at the question of sex or non-sex. And
therefore he is saying, I don’t care if she’s had absolutely no
sex, I don’t care if there’s been no trauma, once her physical
body has changed through puberty, that the hymen is not in its
original state, then I don’t consider her a virgin. I completely just
am concerned about the question about the state of the hymen. So
מוכת עץ Mukat Etz would be a problem. But if that’s true,
anal sex not a problem. Okay, so it’s not at all about
her having had sexual experience, you know, or having had sex, it’s
about the state of the hymen. So we have an extremely narrow
definition of what it means for the hymen to be completely intact,
okay, and very demanding, and it has to be a girl under
age and not מוכת עץ Mukat Etz and nothing physical happened that
ruptured it, etc. Okay, but she could actually have had sexual relations
and not been אסור asur to a כהן Kohen as long as
it had no impact on the hymen. So even anal sex would
not be a problem. Well let me read a little bit more.
Okay, well, so בתולה כדרכה, bitulah kedarkah,
it’s only a problem if it was vaginal sex, שלא כדרכה לא.
shelo kedarkah lo. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון סבי, Rebbi Eliezer v’Rebbi Shimon
Sabi, now that’s not in the משנה, Mishnah, the גמרא Gemara just
sort of spins that out, but it’s fascinating sort of where that,
you know, you know, like a sort of like where that goes
by that having that very demanding criteria but that’s your only criteria.
רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון סבי, Rebbi Eliezer v’Rebbi Shimon Sabi, בתולה, bitulah,
no, they start the opposite position. Had it just said בתולה, bitulah,
בתולה שלמה משמע, bitulah sheleimah mashma,
it would have suggested that the hymen has to be complete. So
that’s what it would have suggested had it just said that. בבתוליה,
bivtuleiha, when it has the extra בבתוליה, bivtuleiha, that’s going in the
opposite direction. אפילו מקצת בתולים, afilu miktzat betulim, even if it’s not
in its original state, even if she actually is a בוגרת, bogeres,
it’s still okay. So not the same demands in terms of the
physical hymen, in terms of the sort of anatomical aspects. אפילו מקצת
בתולים, afilu miktzat betulim, בבתוליה, bivtuleiha, עד שיהיו כל בתוליה קיימים, ad
sheyiyu kol betulim kayamim, בין כדרכה בין שלא כדרכה. bein kedarkah bein
shelo kedarkah.
But the בבתוליה bivtuleiha then says that if there’s something else that’s
going to be a problem, I’ll read it literally about the בתולים,
betulim, then it’s not okay. So if she’s had anal sex, actually,
she is forbidden. Now how anal sex would have any impact on
the hymen and what’s that have to do with the actual physical
of the בתולים betulim is not clear at all. Are they making
some assumption that having anal sex somehow has some impact on the
hymen, etc.? And why would that be different? Like, you know, to
issues of, you know, to other types of concerns, not clear, but
the logic in the end is very clear. What they’re saying is
for us what matters, meaning if you move away from the facts,
in the end it seems to still be talking about the hymen
and you just for a moment step back, you realize what they’re
saying is very logical. For us it’s about her not having had
sex, it’s not about her the hymen being intact. So therefore if
she is has gone through, you know, puberty and somehow the hymen
has changed somewhat, no problem, she’s still a virgin. Okay? However, if
she’s had anal sex, even if it has had no impact on
the hymen, she isn’t a virgin. So it’s about sex, not about
the. So okay. So the question is the מוכת עץ, Mukat Etz,
right? And whether the מוכת עץ Mukat Etz is in the משנה,
Mishnah, is it going on רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון.
Rebbi Shimon. So if they do say a מוכת עץ Mukat Etz
is no good, then they actually would have two separate criteria. An
actual complete rupturing or removal of, you know, the hymen, again I
mentioned that whether that’s actually anatomically correct is a different question, but
anyway, that would also be an issue. Yes, there is a definition
that relates to sort of the hymen being intact. And there’s but
there’s another definition that relates to her not having had sex, to
her being virginal from the other perspective. And since there are so
if you want to frame it that way, since there are two
definitions, we’re not going to go crazy about defining the pristine state
of the hymen. Yes, it’s a criteria, but it’s one of two
criteria and there’s also a basic idea here of her having not
had sex. So therefore we’re not going to go as off, you
know, as extreme as רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir to say the hymen
has to be completely unchanged and she has to be under age.
Okay? So you have רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that it’s all about
the hymen, not about sex. You have רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that it’s either all about sex, or both
about sex and about the hymen, but more reasonable definitions about the
hymen since that’s not what it’s all about.
Then you would have thought that בתולה bitulah can mean that שלא
כדרכה shelo kedarkah also leaves her a בתולה. bitulah. Well what’s בבתוליה
bivtuleiha doing any differently than בתולה? bitulah?
We could have said ואישה בבתולה יקח, v’ishah bivtulah yikach, right? Yeah.
Which then what does, what do you learn out differently from בבתוליה
bivtuleiha that you would have gotten from בתולה? bitulah?
Yeah, it’s a good question. I mean why don’t we just say
בתולה bitulah means מקצת, miktzat, you know like what like you said
מקצת miktzat and then we would have been done.
No, because שלא כדרכה, shelo kedarkah, no,
I don’t know, I can’t fully process.
And one other different question: does it make a difference to them
whether the marriage itself was Rabbinic? Let’s say it was a
בוגרת bogeres and well we’ll get to that. We’ll get to that.
Okay, we’ll get to that. מתיבי רבא. Matvi Rava. So now רבא
Rava asks this. Oh,
I’m sorry, skip twice. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehudah
Amar Rav. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehudah Amar Rav,
נבעלה שלא כדרכה פסולה לכהונה. nivalah shelo kedarkah psulah lekhunah.
Okay, so
let’s say here we go, let’s talk about exactly what we’re talking
about, anal sex. Does that make the woman invalid? Now he says
לכהונה, lekhunah, but he basically... basically means כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay,
so this is exactly what we've tried to frame as the debate
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Obviously our intuitive response would be: Of course she's no
longer a virgin. But what the גמרא Gemara tries to claim or
claims that according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's all about the
physical anatomical reality. And therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say she's
okay. Now obviously the גמרא Gemara is taking the more normal position
that that's not the case, that נבעלה שלא כדרכה פסולה לכהונה. nibala
shelo kedarka psula lekhuna. מתיב רבא. Mativ Rava. So רבא Rava asks:
ולא תהיה לאשה. Velo tiyeh le-isha.
This is about a man who raped a woman that he has
to marry her.
Okay, דאשה הראויה לו. de-isha she-ra'uya lo.
This מצוה mitzvah of marrying her is only if the woman is
fitting to him, meaning halachically fitting. פרט לאלמנה לכהן גדול וגרושה וחלוצה
לכהן הדיוט. Prat l'almana l'kohen gadol, u-grusha v'chalutza l'kohen hedyot.
If a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol rapes an אלמנה almana or a
normal כהן Kohen rapes a גרושה grusha and a חלוצה, chalutza, then
they do not marry them because there's an איסור issur for them
to marry these women. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: היכי דמי?
heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא כדרכה? Ileima ke-darka? How did this
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol rape this אלמנה? almana? It's amazing just imagining
the scene here, or
whatever, I guess with recent events and whatever and other types of
things that we know sadly about religious leaders, it's maybe in certain
ways not as absurd as we would like this to be. So
how did he rape this אלמנה, almana, this אלמנה? almana? If he
did it כדרכה, ke-darka, if it was vaginal, אילימא כדרכה, ileima ke-darka,
מאי איריא משום אלמנה? mai irya mishum almana?
So then why does she just not fit for him because she's
a widow? תיפוק ליה משום דהוה ליה בעולה? Teipokei lei mishum de-hava
lei be-ula?
Before he married her, she's already not a virgin. He's had sex
with her. So even though it's what the גמרא Gemara is going
to call בעולה עצמו, be-ula atzmo, because of his own act, nevertheless
she's not a virgin and he's forbidden to her, right? That's the
state before there's any קידושין. kiddushin. So every normal case of a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, any case of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
raping a woman, it's not אשה הראויה לו, isha re-uya lo, she's
automatically a בעולה. be-ula. So why did he have to find a
case of אלמנה? almana? אלא שלא כדרכה. Ela she-lo ke-darka. It must
be he raped her שלא כדרכה. she-lo ke-darka. And therefore if it
were just because of a בעולה, be-ula, that wouldn't be an issue.
משום אלמנה אין, mishum almana in, and therefore we had to create
the scenario that she was an אלמנה almana to mean that he
can't marry her. משום בעולה לא? mishum be-ula lo? If it was
just about the fact that she was a בעולה, be-ula, that would
not be an issue. So you see that שלא כדרכה she-lo ke-darka
does not make her a
בעולה. be-ula. So the גמרא Gemara says: הא מני רבי מאיר? ha-mani
Rabbi Meir? We just already said that we argued that there is
a position out there like that, that שלא כדרכה she-lo ke-darka does
not make her a בעולה. be-ula. That's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
position who focuses totally on the
hymen. ורב דאמר כרבי אלעזר. Verav de-amar ke-Rabbi Elazar. רב Rav was
saying according to רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Okay, he's explaining רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar or he's פוסק paskening like רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Fine,
that is a רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but we're saying the other
opinion is that שלא כדרכה she-lo ke-darka is invalid for כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Okay. And the משנה Mishnah about a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol and raping an אלמנה, almana, that's according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute: אי כרבי אלעזר,
I ke-Rabbi Elazar, if we're talking within רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar world,
so מאי איריא משום בעולה? mai irya mishum be-ula? Why are you,
do you have to say that if a woman has had anal
sex, she'd be אסור assur to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because
it's a בעולה be-ula according to, you know, not a בתולה betula
according to רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar? Forget the בעולה be-ula בתולה betula
issue. There's a more bigger issue that applies even to a normal
כהן. Kohen. תיפוק ליה דהוה ליה זונה? Teipokei de-hava lei zona? A
woman who's had sex outside of marriage, according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, we don't rule this way, but according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, a woman who's had sex outside of marriage is a זונה
zona and אסור assur to even a normal כהן. Kohen. I mean,
thank God we don't rule that way because you do understand that
a big issue for כהנים, Kohanim, you know, is whether it's women
who are בעלי תשובה ba'alei teshuva or whatever the scenario might be,
you know, a woman who's had sexual experience is that if
she's had sex with a non-Jew, she can't marry a כהן. Kohen.
You know, and you have like these, so you know, I mean,
so once you get through with can't marry גרושה grusha and can't
marry a גיורת giyoret and can't marry a woman who's ever, you
know, had sex with a non-Jew, like you know, it's pretty hard
for כהנים Kohanim to find to you know, to get married. So
if this were true, it wouldn't even be sex with a non-Jew,
anybody who's had any sexual experience couldn't marry a כהן. Kohen. So
that's רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar position. A woman that's had sex with
a non-Jew, with non-Jew, a woman that's had sex outside of marriage
is a זונה. zona. So there why do you have to be
discussing בעולה be-ula and why do you have to be discussing כהן
גדול? Kohen Gadol? You know, if you're talking within רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, that anyway she's אסור assur to a normal כהן. Kohen. So
the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute: תיפוק ליה דהוה ליה זונה.
de-hava lei zona. דאמר רבי אלעזר פנוי הבא על הפנויה, De-amar Rabbi
Elazar penai ha-ba al ha-penuya, even a single man and a single
woman that have sex שלא לשם אישות, she-lo l'shem ishut, if it's
not in the context of marriage, עשאה זונה, asah zona, she's a
זונה. zona. Okay. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say anal sex
is not a problem in terms of בתולה. betula. It's all about
the hymen. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar we said would say it's
a problem, but now we're saying for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar it's
a bigger issue. It's a זונה zona issue. So the גמרא Gemara
says so אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, get ready,
said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, כגון שנבעלה לבהמה, kegon she-niv'ala l'behema, דהכא.
de-hacha. By saying that anal sex makes the woman a non-virgin, how
could you have a case that she's a non-virgin but still not
a זונה zona from Rebbe Eliezer's conception? That she had anal sex
with a בהמה, behema, okay, with an animal. So
therefore זנות znus is a concept in terms of like human people,
human fornication, whereas בעולה beula is more about the physical reality. Of
course again it's a little bit of a problem because since he's
now focusing not on the hymen, it's about the anal sex, you
would think that it's the same definition of a sexual act. If
you consider like we can have right, we can have this discussion,
do would you consider an act of bestiality a forbidden sexual act
or not a sexual act at all, right?
It's just from the תורה, Torah, isn't it?
It's just from the תורה, Torah, but do you put it in
this זנות znus and ביאה biya category, define it somewhat differently? For
example, we had earlier discussions about, not to be too graphic, but
about
העראה, ha-ara, נשיקה, neshika, גמר ביאה, gmar biya, would you say oh
well since העראה ha-ara is the definition of sex for normally it's
also the definition for for bestiality or could you imagine that maybe
we would have a different definition there because it's somehow a different
category? You know, yes it sort of looks the same and whatever,
but maybe הלכתית halachically it's put in its own sui genre, sui
generis category. Anyway, so that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara wants
to sort of split the difference, say for the perspective of איסור
זונה, issur zona, this is a completely like bizarre act and it
would not be considered normal זנות. znus. Normal זנות znus is sleeping
with other human beings. Okay, whereas איסור בעולה issur beula as the
איסור issur
of virgin, she's not a virgin. She's had a sexual act, but
not a זנות znus type of a sexual act. And that's the
case of שלא כדרכה shelo k'darka which makes her a בעולה beula
but doesn't make her a זונה, zona, right? So that's so אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says back the reasonable response. ממנא
נפשך, Mimman nafshach, make up your mind. אי בעולה הויא זונה נמי
הויא. Ee beula havya zona nami havya. If you consider an act
of sex to make her a בעולה beula because again note it's
not about the hymen, it's anal sex, then it also makes her
a זונה. zona. ואי זונה לא הויא, V'ee zona lo havya, and
if she's not a זונה zona because it's not considered to be,
you know, that type of fornication and sexual activity, בעולה נמי לא
הויא. beula nami lo havya. She's not a בעולה, beula, again because
we're not talking about the hymen, we're talking about whether she's had
sex and whether she's had sex or not. So why would we
define sex with an animal one way from the perspective of זנות
znus and another way from the perspective of whether דגברא d'gavra she's
considered a virgin or a בעולה beula or not? Yes? Got a
question? Okay, so that's what אביי Abaye does. He doesn't like the
difference. וכי תימא מידי דהוי אמוכת עץ,
V'chi teima midei d'havya
a-mukkas etz, רבא? Rava? רבא, Rava, he says I'll give you a
case where a woman is not a virgin and she's not a
זונה, zona, מוכת עץ, mukkas etz, right? So, you know, so that's
something
that again it's taken very literally, you know, something actually had protruded
into or was inserted vaginally and ruptured the hymen. So she's not
a בתולה besula but she's also not a זונה. zona. So he
says one minute. So וכי תימא מידי דהוי אמוכת
עץ שלא
כדרכה. V'chi teima midei d'havya a-mukkas etz shelo k'darka. So one minute,
would you say so what he means is not just a normal
מוכת עץ. mukkas etz. A normal מוכת עץ mukkas etz we'd say
fine, ruptures the hymen. But what you're going to say is what
I would what you're going to say is if you want to
make the act of בהמה behema not an act of sex, doesn't
make her a זונה, zona, but because it was שלא כדרכה, shelo
k'darka, even if it's not an act of sex, maybe it had
some impact on the hymen like the גמרא Gemara sort of implied
before, not like we would say. Maybe the act of anal sex
actually does something to the hymen and it is about the hymen.
Oh well if that's true and therefore it's a problem with the
בהמה, behema, logically it should be a problem even about
a מוכת עץ, mukkas etz, even if somebody just stuck something, you
know, anally up there, you know, according to you logically that should
be not a problem of a sex act, but a problem of
a rupturing of the hymen. Is that what you want to say?
If that's what you're going to say that it's not about sex,
the reason this issue of שלא כדרכה shelo k'darka is an issue
is because of something it does to the hymen, well then logically
that should be true even in case מוכת עץ שלא כדרכה. mukkas
etz shelo k'darka. If that's true, אם כן אין לך אשה שכשירה
לכהונה שלא נעשית מוכת עץ על ידי צרור. im ken ein lach
isha she-kesheira l'kehuna she-lo na'asis mukkas etz al yedei tzeror. He
says so a woman anytime you have to go to the bathroom,
you know, and you wipe yourself, and remember they wiped themselves with
rocks, you stick something up there and therefore if you want to
say that that really just the physical sticking of something in there
can rupture the hymen, then no woman would ever be a בתולה
besula okay from that perspective. So obviously when we speak about שלא
כדרכה, shelo k'darka, it is not, and the גמרא Gemara was clarifying
if there was any ambiguity before, it is not because we think
it does anything physically to the hymen. It's because we say the
woman has had sex and that's the definition one of the definitions
of בתולה besula means, you know, virginal in the sense of a
virgin not having had sex. If that's true says the גמרא Gemara
you can't distinguish between if it's an act of sex for making
her בעולה beula versus an act of sex for making her a
זונה, zona, right? It's the same question as whether you want to
treat bestiality in a different category, not in a different category, you
can't split it between these two ideas. Okay? The idea of זונה
zona and the idea. The idea of שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka is
the same question of is it considered an act of sex? It
is not about just the physically what has happened and it's not
about the hymen. So that's a very reasonable response of אביי Abaye
that the גמרא Gemara accepts. We're not going to make a distinction
between those two. So we're back to our question. How does the
woman ever become a בעולה Beulah when it's שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka
without becoming a זונה Zonah according to רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? Once
you consider an act of sex, and she's had sex, if she's
had sex, then outside of marriage, then she's a... then she's also
a זונה, Zonah, she's אסור asur to a normal כהן. Kohein. And
if it's in marriage, well then she's going to be an אלמנה
Almanah or a גרושה, Grushah, so it's moot also, right? How can
she ever be here now discussing her availability to a כהן גדול?
Kohein Gadol? It means she's never been married since we're discussing her
availability to a כהן גדול. Kohein Gadol. How could she have never
been married, be a בעולה Beulah because she's had sex שלא כדרכה,
shelo kedarka, but not be a זונה? Zonah? If she's had sex
with some man she's not married to, she's a זונה Zonah according
to... according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Yeah, we don't פסקן pasken
that way, but according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So אלא אמר
רבי
זירא
Ella Amar
Rabbi Zeira בממאנת. Bi-me-ma-enet. He's got a perfect solution, which Michael anticipated.
I've got the answer! She was a case of a woman, she
was a minor, she was married off by her brother and mother
in a rabbinic קידושין. Kiddushin. So the fact that it is a
rabbinic קידושין Kiddushin means that the sex that she'll be having is
not זנות. zenut. Now that's important, right? Because although when רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says non-marital sex makes a woman a זונה Zonah for
כהונה Kehunah and he's saying it at a דאורייתא De-oraita level,
right? So you would think maybe you need her to be married
in a biblical institution. No, if she's in a marriage that's
a rabbinic marriage, sort of a socially and legally recognized marriage even
though it's not a תורה Torah marriage, but she's in this קידושי
קטנה, Kiddushei Ketanah, that's enough to say that this act is no
longer a ביאת זנות. Bi'at Zenut. And therefore since it's not a
ביאת זנות, Bi'at Zenut, right, she's not a זונה Zonah as a
result. So here she is, she's married to this guy rabbinically. Even
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would concede even though the marriage is only
rabbinic, it's not a ביאת זנות, Bi'at Zenut, she's not a זונה.
Zonah. And now they've only had sex שלא כדרכה, shelo kedarka, okay?
And now when she gets to be twelve years old and now
she goes ahead and she's ממאנת, mema'enet, she goes ahead and she
says, "I don't want this marriage," and she's entitled to do that,
right? Because when she's married off by her mother and her brother.
And then the marriage completely dissolves. It's like retroactively dissolves. She's not
a גרושה, Grushah, she's not an אלמנה, Almanah, retroactively. So it's like
on the one hand retroactively she was never married, so she's מותר
mutar to a כהן. Kohein. On the other hand, the sex that
she had was sex in the context of marriage and therefore she's
not a זונה. Zonah. So in this type of a case, she's
never married, she's had sex, but she's not a זונה Zonah because
it was marital sex, it was not extramarital sex. And now the
only question is, is she a בעולה Beulah or not? And comes
along רב Rav and says, "Yeah, well the שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka
she would still be, she would still be a בעולה Beulah even
though she wouldn't be a זונה Zonah and she could marry a
normal כהן, Kohein, she couldn't marry כהן גדול Kohein Gadol even though
it was only שלא כדרכה shelo kedarka that's still enough to make
her בעולה." Beulah. Those all cases of מאמר Ma'amar would not work
also because she would need a גט, get, she'd have to... she'd
need חליצה, chalitzah, yeah, חליצה chalitzah or גט. get. Right, exactly.
ממאנת mema'enet is the case in which you can retroactively undo it.
Okay,
I just have to show... well, I'll just need to show you
two fascinating things about this. Number one is there's a great רב
חיים Rav Chaim about this case of ממאנת mema'enet because the basic
question you have to ask is like, again, the מה נפשך. mah
nafshach. If it's like she was never married and that allows her
to marry a normal כהן, Kohein, so we're saying retroactively she was
never married. If retroactively she was never married, then why don't we
say that the sex was not in a marital context and she's
a זונה Zonah according to רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? Like make up
your mind. If she was married and now she's not, shouldn't she
be like a rabbinic type of a גרושה? Grushah? How can you
have it retroactively not, but still having her the sex not having
been problematic? So רב חיים Rav Chaim comes up with this idea
which is
called... it's
brilliant. It's called מכאן ולהבא למפרע. mikan u-le-haba le-mafrei-a. Which basically means
למפרע le-mafrei-a means retroactively and מכאן ולהבא mikan u-le-haba means moving forward.
So what he basically says is moving forward retroactively she was never
married. In terms of things that happened in the past, we'd say
they happened in the context of marriage. In terms of all new
questions, we say she was never married.
So... you got it? מכאן ולהבא למפרע mikan u-le-haba le-mafrei-a she was
never married.
Moving forward we'll say she was never married. In terms of things
that already happened, we'll say that happened in the context of marriage.
So she could be married until tomorrow but never yesterday.
Right, exactly. Alright, anyway, one other important thing to say about this
is that there's a lot of interesting issues around questions about potential
solutions to the עגונה agunah problem,
in terms of הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin and קידושין על תנאי. kiddushin
al tnai. And one of the sort of things that pushes against
those are statements in the גמרא Gemara that אין אדם עושה בעילתו
בעילת זנות. Ein Adam oseh b'ilato b'ilat zenut. Nobody would want the
קידושין Kiddushin to be, you know, to be conditional because then retroactively
they were never married, it would turn it into a ביאת זנות
biat zenut etc. A counter argument to that based on this idea
here of ממאנת Mema'enet is that since in the end of the
day, they will have been married in a way that is sort
of recognized in the secular system. And it's one thing in the
גמרא, Gemara, the only marriage that was, the only institution that defined
their relationship was the religious institution of marriage. So if retroactively it
was undone because of a תנאי, tnai, then they were never married
in any way and it would be a ביאת זנות. biat zenut.
But here even if retroactively it's undone as a result of a
תנאי, tnai, they're still legally married, right, and it's an institution that
is recognized communally and it's recognized societally and it's recognized legally. Now
it's true it's not halachically, but you know, but nevertheless is that
enough like this category of ממאנת Mema'enet which is only דרבנן derabbanan
but nevertheless it's enough דאורייתא De'oraita to define it not as a
ביאת זנות biat zenut because it changes, puts the relationship in a
particular type of a structure. Okay so that's an interesting, very relevant
and interesting question from that relates to this גמרא. Gemara. Okay so
now we continue. אמר רב שימי בר חייא, Amar Rav Shimi bar
Chiya, נבוא לה לבהמה, nivo lah l'vehemah, ha! You thought we were
done with that. Now that we figured out that ביאה שלא כדרכה
biah shelo k'darkah even though it doesn't affect the hymen makes her
a non-virgin
except and then we have to find a way where according to
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar it doesn't also make her a זונה. zonah.
Now we're going to go back to this בהמה behemah question. אמר
רב שימי בר חייא, Amar Rav Shimi bar Chiya, נבעלה לבהמה כשרה
לכהונה. niv'alah l'vehemah k'shairah l'kehunah. Okay, so that's a big surprise, right?
Anal sex, no good, that makes her a non-virgin. But an act
of bestiality, okay
then, that is not an act of sex, okay? Like we said,
we said like you can't, right, it wouldn't make her a זונה,
zonah, it wouldn't make her a בעולה. be'ulah. Again, it would have
to be שלא כדרכה shelo k'darkah presumably, right, because if it was
כדרכה k'darkah it would rupture the hymen. Okay, but anyway, it's not
an act of sex. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like
this. And now רש"י Rashi says we're talking about כדרכה k'darkah but
it would assume that מוכת עץ mukat etz is okay. Okay, so
maybe it's an approach that says that even if the hymen is
ruptured it's okay, it's all, right, and therefore even מוכת עץ mukat
etz is okay. It's all about an act of sex and either
way the act with a בהמה behemah is not considered halachically an
act of sex. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we've taught similarly,
נבעלה למי שאינו איש, niv'alah l'mi she'eino ish, if she had sex
with somebody who isn't a man, אף על פי שבסקילה, af al
pi she'bskilah, even though obviously it's a death penalty, כשרה לכהונה, k'shairah
l'kehunah, it's not an act of sex. It's considered something sui generis
and therefore it is not an act of sex and it does
not make her a בעולה. be'ulah. Again, whether it makes her a
מוכת עץ mukat etz depends on your position of מוכת עץ. mukat
etz. If שלא כדרכה shelo k'darkah certainly it's not a problem, it
wouldn't make her a זונה, zonah, it's not considered an act of
sex.
Yes, שאינו איש, she'eino ish, what about an אשה? ishah?
Okay, so that's a good point. It would be it would be
a מוכת עץ mukat etz then, based on whether ביאת
קטן ביאה biat katan biah so would that count also for מוכת
עץ mukat etz with a קטן? katan?
Yeah,
the גמרא Gemara understands that this is just a euphemism because it
doesn't want to say בהמה. behemah.
But what if it wasn't a קטן katan though?
So that's what we're saying, nine years and one day it would,
that's the whole idea, that a ביאת קטן biat katan that would
not. Okay, so כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav Dimi, when
רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said,
מעשה בנערה אחת, ma'aseh b'na'arah achat, a story about a young woman,
בהיתלו, b'Heitlu, in this place called Heitlu, שהיתה מכבדת את הבית, shehayetah
mechabedet et habayit, that she was basically she was you know doing
a wiping herself, it's no,
מכבדת את הבית mechabedet et habayit is a euphemism, wiping herself, okay,
vaginally, ורבץ כלב כופרי מאחוריה, v'ravatz kelev kufri me'achoreiha, and this wild
dog basically raped her,
penetrated her from behind, so that would be a ביאה שלא כדרכה
biah shelo k'darkah
presumably, or מאחוריה me'achoreiha might be vaginally but from behind, והכשירה רבי
לכהונה. v'hichshirah Rebbe l'kehunah. And Rebbe said she can marry a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, yeah fine it was only but it was
only sex with a בהמה. behemah. So therefore she can marry a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Presumably it
was again either he's not concerned about מוכת עץ mukat etz or
it was a it was שלא כדרכה shelo k'darkah and therefore it
did not affect the hymen. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
שמואל לכהן גדול בימי רבי,
כהן גדול מי הוי? Amar Shmuel l'Kohen Gadol bimei Rebbe Kohen Gadol
mi hava? So I don't understand, what do you mean כהונה, kehunah,
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol means that he's מכשר machshir her for
כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? אמר שמואל לכהן גדול בימי רבי Amar Shmuel
l'Kohen Gadol bimei Rebbe, כהן גדול מי הוי? Kohen Gadol mi hava?
So you could have said why are we having this whole discussion,
there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol around?
But the phrasing מכשר machshir sounds like practical פסק. psak. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא ראויה לכהן גדול. Ela re'uyah l'Kohen Gadol.
Fine, theoretically, it wasn't practical.
אמר ליה רבא מפרקין לרב אשי, Amar lei Rava miParquin l'Rav Ashi,
so
רבא Rava מפרקין miParquin or פקוזא, Pakuza, פרוקיא Parukia said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, היכא אמור רבנן, heicha amur Rabbanan, where does this
thing come from that the rabbis say, אין זנות לבהמה, ein zenut
l'vehemah, that an act of sex with an animal is not considered
technically sex? Which is basically what we've been saying, it doesn't make
her a בעולה, be-ulah, it wouldn't make her a זונה, zonah, etc.
דכתיב, De-chsiv, because it says לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב בית
ה' אלהיך, lo savi esnan zonah u-mechier kelev beis hashem elokecha,
do not bring a gift to a prostitute, payment to a prostitute
if a person gives a sheep to a prostitute for her payment,
it cannot be used as a קרבן, korban, and מחיר כלב mechir
kelev for the purchase of a dog, some say, some say that
in פשט, pshat, it's funny פשט pshat because it's not the literal
meaning of the word, but some say nevertheless the פשט pshat meaning
is money paid to a male prostitute. But the חז"ל chazal here
read it very literally and say that if you basically like swap
the sheep for a dog, the sheep is also אסור asur for
a קרבן, korban, literally something used to pay for a dog. Okay,
ותנן u-tenan and we taught in the משנה, mishnah, אתנן כלב esnan
kelev if you reverse this, you actually gave a gift in order
to sleep with a dog, if the dog was prostituting itself, the
owner was prostituting the dog, ומחיר זונה u-mechir zonah or paid money
to purchase a זונה, zonah, whatever that means. Okay, not to purchase
her services, but a type of, no, that's אתנן זונה. esnan zonah.
Okay, אתנן esnan is you give her a sheep as opposed to
money.
Anyway, מותרין, mutarin, that would be permissible, שנאמר, shene-emar, גם שניהם, gam
sheneihem, the two of them. שנים ולא ארבע. shenayim velo arba. So
what do you see from that? Money given for sex with a
dog is not considered to be a problem of אתנן זונה. esnan
zonah. Why not? Why isn't it just money paid for sex? Okay,
so it must be that the act of sex with a dog
is not considered זנות, zenus, is not considered an act of sex.
Now you could have made other distinctions, you know, maybe it's only
אסור asur in a certain type of sex, not all sex. I
mean, what about a male prostitute? Would that be included in אתנן
זונה? esnan zonah? Right? Is it necessarily because we say it's not
an act of sex or just because that's the category the תורה
Torah forbids? But that's what he learns out from the fact that
that's excluded shows that categorically bestiality is a completely different act. Yes.
Like bits of the devil's with an animal animal, the standard of
like having sex, it's not about anatomically about the status of the
hymen and it's not about the penetration, like what is it about?
Like the intimacy with a human? Like what are you using...
No, it is, no, I guess it would just say obviously it's
about the fact that it has, you know, it's obviously about the
fact that this is a live being and it has the genitalia
and so on, but it's just saying that we can't put it
in the same category. You know what I'm... what are you doing?
What makes...
We have to call it something else. We'll call it animal sex,
but we just can't call it sex. We can't just put it
in the same category.
It makes someone else eligible to marry a
כהן, kohen, yes.
Like what is it saying about the different... about... Oh, you mean...
Oh, you mean, why would this type of act, if it's seen
as so like, you know, so heinous or so, you know, whatever,
just completely, you know, you know,
violating so many norms, and that is not... okay, what's worse about
her having had sex with a man? What's different? Yes. You know,
it's a good point. I mean, I've been explaining the גמרא Gemara
in a purely like formalistic way, which is I believe what the
type of discussion the גמרא Gemara is having, like technically do we
call it sex? If we technically don't call it sex, it doesn't
fit in this category, which is about a woman who hasn't had
sex. A woman might have done other bizarre activities, you know, she
might have done, you know, I don't know, witchcraft and חילול שבת
chilul shabbos and a million other forbidden things, but she didn't do
sex. Okay, so you know, but you're starting to say like, okay,
but like explain to me in more human terms, not legal terms,
like what makes it so different, you know? So I don't have
a good answer for that. I mean, this is really a formalistic
type of distinction.
So even if she would be, she did it במזיד, be-mazid, and
explicitly she did it במזיד, be-mazid,
she has to be put to death, because who'd marry her anyway?
Yeah, I mean, let's say there weren't witnesses or התראה hasra-ah or
whatever. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Or you can marry her until she
dies, until she's executed, you know? Maybe, I mean people that marry
people on death row, right?
We've had that, Manson.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Okay.
אנוסת עצמו ומפותת עצמו, Anusas atzmo u-mefusas atzmo, so a כהן גדול
kohen gadol rapes or seduces a woman, so he's had sex with
her, she's a בעולה, be-ulah, but ultimately, but she's a בעולת עצמו.
be-ulas atzmo. So remember, we've already said that he's אסור, asur, it's
not כי אשה בבתוליה יקח. ki ishah bi-vuleha yikach. Although nevertheless that's
not...
he's violating the מצוה mitzvah of marrying a virgin, לא ישא, lo
yisa, so he's not allowed to marry her. Nevertheless, אם נשא נשא,
im nasa nasa, if he married her, he can stay married. Now
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
does with...
was it relations with her after he was married?
No, no, that would... well, that does go a little bit back
to the question before, whether you define it as קידושין kiddushin or
נישואין. nisuin. But let's... so that in a way was yesterday's question,
let's bracket it. Okay, so אם נשא נשא. im nasa nasa. אנוסת
חבירו ומפותת חבירו, Anusas chaveiro u-mefusas chaveiro, if this woman has had
sex with another man, so also presumably it's the same halachic problem,
she's not a בתולה, besulah, it's a מצות עשה mitzuas asei of
כי אשה בבתוליה יקח. ki ishah bi-vuleha yikach. והלכה Ve-halacha is very
different. לא ישא, lo yisa, do not marry, ואם נשא, ve-im nasa,
if he did marry, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר הולד חלל, Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov omer ha-vlad chalal, the child is a חלל, chalal,
doesn't have קדושת כהונה kedushat kehunah because he's violating the מצות עשה
mitzuas asei of אשה בבתוליה יקח. ishah bi-vuleha yikach. וחכמים אומרים הולד
כשר, Ve-chachamim omrim ha-vlad kasher, the ולד vlad is כשר. kasher. So
here we have two interesting things. Number one is we know in
general that the child is a חלל chalal when the כהן kohen
violates the one of the forbidden marriages of כהונה, kehuna, but that's
almost always a לאו, lav, גרושה, gerusha, אלמנה, almanah, etc. זונה, zonah,
what about when it is violating the עשה, aseh, the one מצות
עשה mitzvat aseh that limits marriage, and that's a כהן גדול kohen
gadol needs to marry a בתולה, betulah, to not marry a non-בתולה.
betulah. If that's violated, she's not an אלמנה, almanah, she's not a
גרושה, gerusha, etc., is the child a חלל chalal or not? So
that's the debate here between רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov and the חכמים. Chachamim. But the other question is, why is
that not the same issue when it's a woman that he's had
sex with? Nevertheless, same issue, right? Same story. It's still the
איסור עשה, issur aseh, אשה בבתוליה. isha bivsuleha. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אי נשא נשא, Ei nasa nasa, so
the גמרא Gemara is now going to unpack this. First stage is
they can stay married if it was a woman that he's had
sex with. אמר רב הונא אמר רב ומוציא בגט. Amar Rav Huna
amar Rav u-motzi ve-get. Now he has to divorce her. Or he
didn't say no. You know what, I once took this improv course
and the basic
strategy or whatever, the basic method they teach you is, you know,
normally in life we say no, but, and in improv you're always
supposed to say yes, and. Okay, so somebody says something and you
don't say no, but, you know, something else, you say yes, and
this. So rather than, so here רב Rav is not saying, oh
no, they can't stay married, he has to get a גט. get.
Yes, they're married, and he has to give her a גט. get.
So there you go, yes, and. Okay, אמר רב הונא אמר רב
ומוציא בגט. Amar Rav Huna amar Rav u-motzi ve-get. Fine, they're married,
but he has to, and, not but, and he has to give
her a גט. get. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute,
what does that mean that they're married? I mean, there's no חידוש
chiddush that the marriage is binding, right? Even by an איסור לאו,
issur lav, even by a גרושה, gerusha, the marriage is binding, right?
בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, the marriage, you know, בדיעבד, bedi'avad, the marriage is legally
binding and you need a גט. get. So if they're obligated to
give a גט, get, what's the חידוש? chiddush? Of course the marriage
is binding, so what are you trying to say that they're married?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא הא דקתני אי נשא נשא, Ela
ha de-katani ei nasa nasa, so what does that mean when we
say they're married, which sounds like, you know, that you don't have
to get a גט? get? So אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar
Rav Acha bar Yaakov, לומר, lomar, to tell you top of ס"ח
עמוד א, samech chet amud aleph, so we're getting a little bit
caught up, שאין משלמין קנס דמפותה. she-ein meshalmin knas de-mefuta. Let's say
he seduced her and now she's a בעולת עצמו, be'ulat atzmo, and
the הלכה halakha is if he chooses to marry her, he doesn't
pay the קנס, knas, right? That's the story about a man who
seduces a woman. If he rapes her, he pays the fine and
he marries her. If he seduces her, he either pays the fine
or he marries her. So here the question is, if he goes
ahead and chooses to marry her, then that's a way of getting
out of paying the קנס. knas. We would actually say that as
opposed to a case of when it was like an איסור לאו
issur lav that would not be considered a valid marriage, again, it
would be binding, you would need a גט get and so on,
but it would not be considered a licit marriage and therefore would
not get him out of paying a קנס. knas. Here it would
get him out of paying a קנס. knas. But as far as
rabbinically are we going to tolerate this situation? We're not going to
tolerate this situation. Since it's an איסור עשה, issur aseh, even though
it was a woman he himself had sex with, you have to
go ahead and give a
גט. get. Okay, אתא רב גביהא מבי כתיל, Ata Rav Geviha mi-bei
Katil, and אמרה לשמעתא קמיה דרב אשי, amrah le-shmata kamei de-Rav Ashi,
and he went and told this discussion over to רב אשי Rav
Ashi that, you know, רב Rav said, yes, they're married, but you
have to, and you have to give a גט. get. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, ורב ורבי יוחנן דאמרי תרווייהו, ve-Rav ve-Rabbi Yochanan de-amri
tarvaihu, what, רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan both say, בוגרת
ומוכת עץ לא ישא, bogeret u-mukat etz lo yisa, ואם נשא נשא,
ve-im nasa nasa, that a כהן גדול kohen gadol should not marry
a בוגרת bogeret and a מוכת עץ, mukat etz, again, if it
doesn't have the hymen intact, but if he did marry, they are
allowed to stay married. Now what's the logic? If it's just considered
an איסור עשה issur aseh of not being a בתולה, betulah, why
should they be allowed to stay married בדיעבד? bedi'avad? So now here
we have a fascinating answer. אמר סופא להיות בוגרת תחתיו,
Amar sofa
lihyot bogeret tachtav, סופא להיות מוכת עץ תחתיו. sofa lihyot mukat etz
tachtav. The reason we don't force a divorce in those cases is
because in the end every woman he marries as a בתולה betulah
is hopefully pretty soon not going to be, well depending on how
old she is, but anyway sooner or later not going to be
a בתולה. betulah. So can we tolerate the fact that right now
he's married to a non-בתולה? betulah? Yes, because always he's going to
be married to a non-בתולה betulah pretty soon after the marriage. So
the problem is the moment of getting married, not the state of
being married to a non-בתולה. betulah. So if that's true, what we
say about the case about בדיעבד, bedi'avad, right? He wasn't allowed to
marry a בוגרת bogeret and a מוכת עץ, mukat etz, but once
he did, we can tolerate it, because anyway, that's, you know, that's
the normal situation that's going to be. So here too, why don't
we tolerate it בדיעבד? bedi'avad? So הכא נמי סופא להיות בעולה תחתיו.
hacha nami sofa lihyot be'ulah tachtav. Let's tolerate it at least בדיעבד.
bedi'avad. So that's difficult. Now the interesting question, you know, again, that's
not clear in the גמרא Gemara is like, does he biblically continue
to be עובר, over, but it's a question whether rabbinically we're going
to do anything about it. Like a כהן גדול kohen gadol marries
a non-בתולה, betulah, how many times is he עובר? over? Every time
he has sex? The first act of marriage? Right, a reasonable thing
to conclude from this גמרא Gemara is the first act of... A
reasonable thing to conclude from this גמרא Gemara is the first act
of marriage is when he's עובר, over, because as the גמרא Gemara
says, after the first act of sex anyway, any woman, even if
she was a virgin to begin with, he'd be having ongoing sex
with her, she'd be not a virgin. So it's hard to imagine
that every single act of sex he continues to be עובר over
defined by the initial moment that they were married, right? But that's
another question to ask. There's two questions. One is like rabbinically are
we able to tolerate it and are we going to force them
to get divorced? And the other is like biblically does he is
he transgressing, you know, in this ongoing situation. It's reasonable to assume
that the answer to the first one is certainly we do tolerate
it. It's reasonable to assume that the answer to the second one
is also that he is not transgressing on an ongoing basis. And
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara somehow says we don't understand, but why we
are lenient in the case of בוגרת ומאוסה bogeret u'me'usa somehow in
the case of בעולת עצמו beulat atzmo we won't be lenient. And
the answer seems to be more at a societal level. Like we
don't want to sort of have like a חוטא נשכר, choteh niskar,
you know, in one case like he didn't do anything... he did
something wrong in the marriage, but it wasn't like there was general
inappropriate activity. Here there was some general inappropriate activity, maybe we don't
want to continue to tolerate the situation. Okay, so that's the question
about whether rabbinically we're going to do anything about it. המנוסת חברו
ומפותת חברו לא ישא ואם נשא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר הולד
חלל וחכמים אומרים הולד כשר. ha-menuset chavero u-mefutat chavero lo yisa ve-im
nasa rabbi eliezer ben yaakov omer ha-vlad chalal va-chachamim omrim ha-vlad kasher.
Now we deal with the בדיעבד be-di'avad situation if somebody has violated
the עשה, aseh, what's the story about the child? Okay, now again
what's fascinating is going back to my earlier question when רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says הולד חלל, ha-vlad chalal, presumably
that's a child that's born not, you know, even after the first
act of sex, not just the initial, like initial act of sex
is, you know, would be the definition. So it's certainly also clear
from that question that it seems like according to at least רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov on an ongoing basis he's
considered to be violating, right? Because they could be... she could conceive
a year into the marriage. Okay, normal any woman, no matter how
he married her, a year into the marriage she's no longer a
virgin. But nevertheless this woman, since she started as not a virgin,
a year into the marriage she's still doing an איסור issur living
with her or having sex with her, and therefore the child is
a חלל. chalal. It might be according to that that he's transgressing
not just at the moment of sex, but during the marriage. Right,
constantly every second. Right, and that is a general question about איסורי
כהונה. issurei kehuna. How much is איסורי כהונה issurei kehuna linked to
being married and how much is it about having sex or some
combination of the two? So we haven't fully explored that, but that
is an ongoing question by איסורי כהונה. issurei kehuna. אמר רב הונא
אמר רב הלכה כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Amar Rav Huna amar Rav
halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We rule this way. וכן אמר רב
גידל אמר רב Ve-chen amar Rav Giddal amar Rav because of כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, right. וכן אמר רב גידל אמר רב הלכה כרבי
אליעזר בן יעקב. Ve-chen amar Rav Giddal amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some say אמר רב הונא אמר
רב מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Amar Rav Huna amar Rav
mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We're not ruling, but we're exploring
his idea, his opinion. What's his reason? סבר לה כרבי אליעזר. Savar
lah ke-Rabbi Eliezer. He feels like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So meaning
which is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says that פנוי הבא על
הפנויה עשאה זונה. panui ha-ba al ha-penuya asaa zona. So he actually
says no, no, no, you got it totally wrong. He's not saying
the child is a חלל chalal because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
violated the עשה aseh of marrying a virgin. The child is a
חלל chalal because she had premarital sex with another guy. Remember this
is בעולת עצמו. beulat atzmo. She had premarital sex with another guy.
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that she's a זונה. zona. And
that's why she's a... the child is a חלל. chalal. That would
be חלל chalal if she was married to a normal כהן, Kohen,
not only a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. ומי סבר לה כוותיה? U-mi savar lah kavatei? Does
he really hold by him? והא קיימא לן משנת רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב קב ונקי. Ve-ha kayma lan mishnat Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov kav
ve-naki. We say the teaching of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov is like a small quantity but very clean like grain,
meaning that he says very little but what he says we will
like it. So if he's saying like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you
would force us to say that we rule like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. ואילו בהא, Ve-ilu be-ha, but when it comes to רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer's position, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רב אין הלכה
כרבי אליעזר. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rav ein halacha ke-Rabbi
Eliezer. We don't rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which as I
said is a very good thing, because it would mean any woman
who has ever had any sexual history would never be able to
marry a כהן. Kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא, kashya, that's
difficult. So this was one attempt to explain רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that the child is a חלל chalal having
nothing to do with the עשה, aseh, having to do with the
fact that she had sex with another man made her into a
זונה zona and it would have been true even by a non-כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, and רב אשי
Rav Ashi says the best... simpler explanation of this debate. ביש חלל
מחייבי עשה קמיפלגי. Be-yesh chalal mi-chayvei aseh kamifligi. The debate is, is
there a חלל chalal that does a child conceived through a prohibited
act only prohibited as an עשה, aseh, a sexual act, an איסור
כהונה issur kehuna of an עשה, aseh, which is specifically the only
one that exists is the idea of marrying a virgin for a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, does that also produce a חלל? chalal? רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב סבר יש חלל מחייבי עשה ורבנן סברי אין חלל
מחייבי עשה. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov savar yesh chalal mi-chayvei aseh ve-rabanan
savri ein chalal mi-chayvei aseh. That's the simple debate. מאי טעמא דרבי
אליעזר בן יעקב? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov? Where does רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov get the idea that a
חלל chalal emerges even from transgressing the עשה? aseh? Because it says,
דכתיב, de-chtiv, the verse says אלמנה וגרושה וחללה זונה את אלה לא
יקח כי אם בתולה מעמיו יקח אשה. almana u-grusha ve-chalala zona et
eleh lo yikach ki im betula me-amav yikach isha. Don't marry a
חללה, chalala, גרושה, grusha, etc., that's the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. Only
marry a בתולה. betula. וכתיב, U-chtiv, and it says in the next
פסוק, pasuk, ולא יחלל זרעו בעמיו, ve-lo yechalel zaro be-amav, and let
him not desecrate his seed, his children. So you see any violation
And results in the child being a חלל. challal. אכולו, a kulo,
go learn everything. רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis say no. אלה הפסיק העניין.
eleh hifsik ha'inyan. It says אלמנה וגרושה חללה זונה את אלה לא
יקח, almanah ugrushah challalah zonah et eleh lo yikach, so אלה eleh
underscores that those are the ones that are really problematic. כי אם
בתולה מעמיו יקח אשה ki im betulah me'amav yikach ishah is like
okay, that's what he should do and that's a מצות עשה, mitzvas
aseh, but it's not in the real problematic category and therefore it
sets him off as a different category and only from that emerges
a חלל. challal. Okay, הפסיק העניין, hifsik ha'inyan, that interrupts the list.
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אמר אלה נו, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov amar
eleh nu, אלה eleh is coming to do something else, למעוטי נידה,
le'mautei niddah, that if he, כהן, kohen, had sex with his wife
and she's a נידה, niddah, although that's an איסור כרת, issur karet,
that does not produce a חלל, challal, because even because again it's
a very weighty איסור issur but it's not about marriage and it's
something that, you know, it's temporary, it's not about a status. Okay.
כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, keman azla ha detanya, who goes like that
which we taught in the ברייתא? baraita? מאלה אתה עושה חלל ואי
אתה עושה חלל מנידה, me'eleh attah oseh challal ve'ei attah oseh challal
mi'niddah, only these women create a חלל challal but not a נידה.
niddah. כמאן? keman? כרבי אלעזר בן יעקב, k'Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, like
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, because he would say
even from a non-בתולה betulah comes a חלל challal and the only
excluded category is נידה. niddah. ולרבי אלעזר בן יעקב נכתבי אלה לבסוף?
u'l'Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov nichtivei eleh l'vasof? So we have the question:
if they're all equal in terms of this issue of a חלל,
challal, why doesn't the word אלה eleh come at the end, why
does it interrupt the two categories? קשיא. kashya. All right, I don't
know the answer. Moving on. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, אחותו ארוסה. achoto
arusah. Now we're moving on to a, we're putting aside, we're moving
beyond this ברייתא, baraita, going on to a new topic. I mean
not totally new, but okay. Okay, the תורה Torah says, right, that
a כהן גדול kohen gadol is מטמא, metamei, who is he מטמא
metamei to? Or a כהן kohen is מטמא, metamei, who is he
מטמא metamei to? It says לאחותו הבתולה הקרובה אליו אשר לא הייתה
לאיש. l'achoto ha'betulah ha'kerovah elav asher lo hayetah l'ish. So she has
to be בתולה, betulah, she has to be לא הייתה לאיש. lo
hayetah l'ish. So we talk about what if she's a מוכת עץ,
mukat etz, right? That's one obvious question. But what if, but the
question is is she a בתולה? betulah? Okay, so she's a בתולה.
betulah. But what about, those were two phrases, but what about if
she is ארוסה arusah and not נשואה? nesuah? Would that, would he
still be מטמא metamei to her? When the כהן גדול kohen gadol
is מטמא metamei to the קרובים, kerovim, the sister, to what extent
is she still part of his family or part of another man's
family? Okay, so what if she's an ארוסה, arusah, not נשואה? nesuah?
Is he מטמא metamei to her? Okay, so תנו רבנן אחותו ארוסה
רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה אומרים מטמא לה רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים
אין מטמא לה. tanu rabbanan achoto arusah Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehuda omrim
metamei lah Rabbi Yossi v'Rabbi Shimon omrim ein metamei lah. So it's
a debate of those תנאים. tannaim. Now how about אנוסה ומפותה, anusah
u'mifutah, let's say she's had sex? דברי הכל אין מטמא לה. divrei
ha'kol ein metamei lah. Okay, everybody agrees. It said בתולה אשר לא
הייתה לאיש. betulah asher lo hayetah l'ish. ומוכת עץ, u'mukat etz, but
what if she doesn't have her hymen but not as a result
of sex? Like the question we had by כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
So the same way we could ask it by כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, these fascinating questions, we can ask it about the הלכה halacha
that a כהן kohen is becomes טמא tamei to his sister who's
a virgin. What defines virginity in that context sense? What if she's
a מוכת עץ, mukat etz, there's no hymen, would he be מטמא
metamei to her? So ומוכת עץ אין מטמא לה דברי רבי שמעון.
u'mukat etz ein metamei lah divrei Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would say he's not מטמא. metamei. שהיה רבי שמעון אומר ראויה לכהן
גדול מטמא לה שאינה ראויה לכהן גדול אין מטמא לה. she'hayah Rabbi
Shimon omer rauyah l'kohen gadol metamei lah she'einah rauyah l'kohen gadol ein
metamei lah. It follows the category of כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So
therefore and for and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon goes by his position
because we said before that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that
a woman who's a מוכת עץ mukat etz is not fit for
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, okay? So therefore that, so therefore he
says same definition and therefore since a מוכת עץ mukat etz is
not fit for a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, so also a normal
כהן kohen would not be מטמא metamei to her. ובוגרת מטמא לה
דברי כל אדם. u'vogeret metamei lah divrei kol adam. So ובוגרת, u'vogeret,
he would be מטמא metamei to her, says כל אדם. kol adam.
Now that's fascinating. דברי הכל? divrei hakol? I know, but we know
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir normally says that by כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, בוגרת vogeret is out of the category. Here everybody would agree
בוגרת vogeret is in the category. Can you remind me why that
would be out of the category? Meaning that it's not considered a
בתולה. betulah. But here everybody agrees a בוגרת vogeret is considered a
בתולה. betulah. Now we, now let's go back and understand everybody's reasonings
in all these various debates. Let's start with the debate of if
she's an ארוסה. arusah. She's and never had sex, but she's an
ארוסה. arusah. מאי טעמייהו דרבי מאיר ורבי יהודה? mai ta'amayhu d'Rabbi Meir
v'Rabbi Yehuda? Why do רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda say that the כהן kohen is still מטמא metamei to her
sister after she's an ארוסה? arusah? דדרשי הכי, didrashi hachi, they explain
the פסוקים psukim the following way: לאחותו הבתולה פרט לאנוסה ומפותה. l'achoto
ha'betulah prat l'anusah u'mifutah. Simply, virgin, hasn't had sex. יכול שאני מוציא
אף מוכת עץ, yachol she'ani motzi af mukat etz, maybe even if
the hymen has been ruptured she'd be excluded, which we know is
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to say. So again maybe
it's anatomical, it's not just the issue of sex. תלמוד לומר אשר
לא הייתה לאיש מי שהוייתה על ידי איש. talmud lomar asher lo
hayetah l'ish mi she'havayatah al yedei ish. So here it defines, whatever
you might say by a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, here it sees
these two phrases not as saying different things but as defining one
another. What does בתולה betulah mean in this context? Right, it's like
it says by רבקה, Rivka, בתולה ואיש לא ידעה. betulah v'ish lo
yeda'ah. So רש"י Rashi says it means two different things, okay? So
here what it says, it's defining. What does it mean בתולה? betulah?
It means אשר לא הייתה לאיש. asher lo hayetah l'ish. Vitality's. It's
about sex, it's not about the hymen. The second phrase explains the
first one. יצא זו שאינה בתולה על ידי איש Yatza zu she'eina
besulah al yedei ish to exclude the case about the hymen rupturing,
that's not a problem. Okay, so now we've got the idea that
it's all about sex. What about this issue of ארוסה? arusa? הקרובה
Hakrova that's close to him, לרבות ארוסה. lerabbos arusa. Somehow you could
say קרובה krova is excluding an ארוסה arusa she's already halfway out
the door. Somehow they learned that the word קרובה krova is somehow
including the ארוסה arusa that he still מטמא metamei to her because
she's still close enough to him even as an ארוסה. arusa. אליו
Eilav again to him and לרבות את הבוגרת. lerabbos es habogeres. That's
going to say that even a בוגרת bogeres again because which makes
sense they're not so concerned about the physical hymen מוכת עץ mukkas
eitz so certainly they're going to include a בוגרת bogeres as well.
Okay, that's not much of a חידוש. chiddush. Once you say מוכת
עץ mukkas eitz isn't the problem it's pretty obvious בוגרת bogeres isn't
the problem. So it's not exactly clear why they learned those פסוקים
pesukim to be more inclusive rather than exclusive but nevertheless for them
it's all about sex. Okay, and therefore בוגרת bogeres isn't the problem,
ארוסה arusa isn't the problem, it's all about מוכת עץ mukkas eitz
isn't the problem etc. הא למה לי קרא Ha lama li kra
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, and that's what they
have. הא למה לי קרא Ha lama li kra one minute why
do you need a פסוק? pasuk? והאמר רבי מאיר בתולה אפילו מקצת
בתולה משמע. Veha'amar Rabbi Meir besulah afilu miktzas besulah mashma. Why do
you need a פסוק pasuk to say by a בוגרת bogeres that
to include? Wouldn't it... it says הבתולה habesulah and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says בתולה besulah is even מקצת בתולה miktzas besulah which means
even a בוגרת bogeres as that's how we explained earlier. איצטריך Itztrich
no you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא ילמד בתולה בתולה מהתם. Salka
da'atach amina yilmad besulah besulah mehasam. Let's learn out from כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Like כהן גדול Kohen Gadol בוגרת bogeres is not considered
a בתולה. besulah. מה להלן נערה אף כאן נערה. Ma lehalan na'arah
af kan na'arah. So קמ"ל kamashma lan not that way that even
if by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol we focus on the hymen etc.
here we have a different standard so the same רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol said a ruptured hymen is
a problem here he would say it's all about sex and therefore
I don't care בוגרת, bogeres, I don't care מוכת עץ, mukkas eitz,
I don't care ארוסה. arusa. That's as long as she hasn't had
sex fine it's not the same standard as a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Let's just we're already over let's just see literally one more
one more section here. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון מאי טעמא? Rabbi Yosei
veRabbi Shimon mai ta'ama? Now why do רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that ארוסה arusa is a problem? דרשי
הכי ולאחותו הבתולה פרט לארוסה Darshi hachi velachoso habesulah prat la'arusa you
know what we will stop here. Okay, so we got that position
that says it's all about sex by the sister, we will now
see the other opinion that forbids ארוסה arusa and we'll pick up
with this tomorrow.